# Linton Freund, PhD

805-444-2337 | lintonfreund@gmail.com | Poway, CA, 92064 https://github.com/hlfreund | https://hlfreund.github.io

#### **ABOUT**

I am a trained bioinformatician with seven years of experience in analyzing a variety of sequence data types. I have worked with iTag (i.e., amplicon) and shotgun metagenome sequence data, and I have also developed workflows in Bash shell and R statistical software that walk users through how to process and analyze their data using bioinformatic tools and statistical analyses, most notably model-based analyses. I am passionate about creating and using an accessible, interdisciplinary approach with bioinformatics and statistics to address important questions about environmental health, public health, and their intersections.

#### **EDUCATION**

## PhD., Genetics, Genomics, & Bioinformatics

Sep 2024

University of California, Riverside; Riverside, CA

Dissertation Title: The Microbial Ecology of the Salton Sea: How an Extreme Environment Selects for Microbial Metabolism & Survival

MSc., Biology May 2019

California State University, Long Beach; Long Beach, CA

Thesis Title: Insights into the Structure and Function of the Gut Metagenome in Cartilaginous Fishes

As., Biology May 2017

Moorpark College; Moorpark, CA

BA., Psychology June 2014

University of California, Santa Barbara; Santa Barbara, CA

## **WORK & RESEARCH EXPERIENCE**

## **Graduate Student Researcher**

Aug 2019 - Sep 2024

Supervisor: Dr. Emma Aronson

Microbiology & Plant Pathology Department, University of California, Riverside

- Led and designed experiments investigating the Salton Sea microbial community and microbial biogeochemical cycling using a multidisciplinary, collaborative approach.
- Extract and quantify DNA extracts for amplicon and shotgun metagenome sequencing.
- Process and analyze amplicon and shotgun sequencing metagenomic data with bioinformatic tools, custom Bash shell scripts, and custom workflows using R statistical software and RMarkdown.
- Perform statistical analyses on amplicon sequence data, metagenome sequence data, and geochemistry data using R statistical software packages and custom R scripts.

#### **Graduate Student Researcher**

Aug 2017 - May 2019

Supervisor: Dr. Renaud Berlemont

Microbiology Department, California State University, Long Beach

- Processed raw (unassembled) metagenome sequence data via bioinformatics tools such as MG-RAST and custom Bash shell scripts.
- Statistically analyzed raw metagenome sequence data via custom R scripts and R packages.
- Investigated microbial, enzymatic polysaccharide deconstruction in the gut of vertebrates.
- Assisted Principal Investigator in writing, editing, and reviewing lab publications such as literature reviews and bioinformatics workflows.

## **Contract Biologist**

Jun 2016 - Jan 2017

Supervisor: Dr. Jana Johnson

The Butterfly Project, Moorpark College

- Captured endangered, gravid foundresses and released pupae in the field.
- Performed and supervised feedings of the endangered butterflies.
- Monitored butterfly oviposition and mapped locations of butterfly eggs.

Built habitats for larvae, pupae, and butterflies respectively and cared for the foliage included in these
habitats.

Student Intern Feb 2016 – Apr 2016

Supervisor: Dr. Subhash Karkare

Biotechnology Department, Moorpark College

- Prepared cytotoxic T-lymphocyte associate protein 4 samples for troubleshooting the Biotechnology Department's enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (i.e., ELISA) protocol.
- Developed an ELISA protocol to reduce the time of the ELISA for a Moorpark College Biotechnology Certificate course.
- Researched the purpose and technique behind the ELISA for the associated lesson plan.
- Recorded qualitative analysis of ELISA results to include for the ELISA lesson plan & protocol.

#### **Lead Clinical Research Coordinate**

Jun 2014 – Aug 2014

Supervisor: Luna Yojay, PharmD.

LY Pharmacy Inc.

- Supervised and recorded the administration of trial pharmaceuticals, specifically medications that target chronic kidney disease, to dialysis patients participating in our trials.
- Monitored vital signs of patients after the trial pharmaceuticals were administered.
- Met with Clinical Research Associates to update them on the incoming results from our patients.
- Recorded and managed trial data utilizing the electronic data-capture Medidata Rave.

## **Undergraduate Research Assistant**

Sep 2013 - Jun 2014

Supervisor: Dr. F. Gregory Ashby

Psychological and Brain Sciences Department, University of California, Santa Barbara

- Designed and conducted an independent research project that focused on how and when the prefrontal cortex swithces between procedural verses declarative learning.
- Collected and organized data from graduate students' respective experiments.
- Observed and assisted graduate students in data analysis of computer-based experiments using MATLAB.
- Supervised computational-based experiments for graduate students that targeted procedural and declarative learning systems in the prefrontal cortex.

#### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

Teaching Assistant Jan 2024 – Mar 2024

Introduction to Cell and Molecular Biology, BIOL 005A

Supervisor: Dr. David Fronk

Microbiology & Plant Pathology Department, University of California, Riverside

- Reviewed course material with undergraduate students as lectures and as worksheets that were completed in class.
- Worked with fellow teaching assistants, the instructors, and the academic coordinator to create and grade quizzes.

Teaching Assistant Apr 2021 – June 2021

Introduction to Microbiology Lab, MCBL 121L

Supervisor: Dr. James Borneman

Microbiology & Plant Pathology Department, University of California, Riverside

- Lectured on basic microbiology lab techniques and the science behind them, including DNA extraction, DNA purification, and sequencing library amplification using PCR.
- Reviewed and graded lab exams and laboratory notebooks that students used to record their respective experiments and results.

Teaching Assistant Feb 2018 – May 2018

Introduction to Evolution and Diversity Lab, BIOL 211L

Supervisor: Lindsay Darjany, MS.

Biology Department, California State University, Long Beach

- Created and presented lectures that covered basic concepts from biology and ecology.
- Led students through in-class lab activities that reinforced the concepts covered in our lab lectures.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

Aronson, E. L., **Freund, H. L.**, and Maltz, M. R. 2023. Microbiology of the Critical Zone. Critical Zone and Ecosystem Dynamics, White, T. and A. Provenzale, Eds. Springer-Verlag. *in press.* 

Freund, L. (2023). Amplicon Sequencing Workflow (v1.0.1). Zenodo. https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8264886

Biddle, T.A., Yisrael, K., Drover, R., Li, Q., Maltz, M.R., Topacio, T.M., Yu J., Del Castillo, D., Gonzales, D., **Freund, H.L.**, Swenson, M.P., Shapiro, M.L., Botthoff, J.K., Aronson, E., Cocker, D.R. 3rd, Lo D.D. Aerosolized aqueous dust extracts collected near a drying lake trigger acute neutrophilic pulmonary inflammation reminiscent of microbial innate immune ligands. Sci Total Environ. 2023 Feb 1;858(Pt 3):159882. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159882. Epub 2022 Nov 2. PMID: 36334668.

Maltz, M.R.; Carey, C.J; **Freund, H.L.**; Botthoff, J.; Stajich, J.E.; Hart, S.C.; Aarons S.; Aciego, S.; Blakowski, M.; Cullen Dove, N.D.; Barnes, M; Pombubpa N.; Aronson, E. Landscape topography and regional drought alters dust microbiomes in the Sierra Nevada of California. Frontiers in Microbiology 2022 13:856454.

**Freund H.L.**, Maltz M.R., Swenson, M.P., Topacio, T.M., Montellano, V.A., Porter, W., Aronson, E. Microbiome interactions and their ecological implications at the Salton Sea. California Agriculture 2022 76: 1.

Jackson, D.; Maltz, M.R.; **Freund, H.L.**; Borneman, J.; Aronson, E. Environment and Diet Influence the Bacterial Microbiome of Ambigolimax valentianus, an Invasive Slug in California. Insects 2021 12: 7.

Nguyen, S. T. C., **Freund, H. L.**, Kasanjian, J., and Berlemont, R. 2018. Function, distribution, and annotation of characterized cellulases, xylanases, and chitinases from CAZy. Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology 102: 4.

#### **AWARDS**

Dissertation Completion Fellowship Award University of California, Riverside \$10,000	2024
Dr. Mir S. Mulla & Leila Mulla Endowed Scholarship Fund University of California, Riverside, College of Natural Sciences \$12,000	2024
Best Poster Presentation Annual Genetics, Genomics, and Bioinformatics Symposium: "Microbial Function and Diversity in a Hypersaline Lake" \$100	2023
Dean's Fellowship Fund Award University of California, Riverside, College of Natural Sciences \$6,200	2023
NMDC Champion National Microbiome Data Collaborative	2022
Workshop Scholarship University of Washington, Summer Institute of Statistical Genetics \$900	2021
Dr. Janet M Boyce Memorial Endowed Scholarship Fund University of California, Riverside, College of Natural Sciences \$2,000	2021

Best Flash-Talk 2020

Annual Genetics, Genomics, and Bioinformatics Symposium: "Investigating the Aeolian Microbiome of the Salton Sea"

\$50

Chancellor's Distinguished Fellowship

University of California, Riverside, College of Natural Sciences

2019

Dr. Vern Eveland Memorial Award California State University, Long Beach \$2.500 2018

Linda Lee Warren Graham Endowed Scholarship California State University, Long Beach \$2,000

2018

#### SELECTED PRESENTATIONS

**Linton Freund,** Talyssa Topacio, Dr. Yaning Miao, Will Porter, Mark Swenson, Dr. Mia Maltz, Jon Bothoff, Dr. Emma Aronson. The Core Aeolian Microbiome and its Pathogenic Potential. Poster Presentation, Beyond the Haze: A Symposium on Dust Impacts on Climate, the Environment and Human Health. May 2024, Davis, California.

**Linton Freund**, Caroline Hung, Talyssa Topacio, Dr. Charlie Diamond, Alyson Fresquez, Dr. Tim Lyons, Dr. Emma Aronson. Microbial Function and Diversity in a Hypersaline Lake. Poster presentation, Center for Microbiome Innovation International Microbiome Meeting. March 2024, La Jolla, California.

**Linton Freund**, Caroline Hung, Talyssa Topacio, Dr. Charlie Diamond, Alyson Fresquez, Dr. Tim Lyons, Dr. Emma Aronson. Microbial Function and Diversity in a Hypersaline Lake. Poster presentation, 9th Annual Southern California Microbiome Symposium. September 2023, Riverside, California.

**Linton Freund**, Talyssa Topacio. The Microbial Connection Between Dust & Health in the Salton Sea. Oral presentation, BREATHE Annual Workshop. May 2022, Riverside, California.

**Linton Freund**. Microbiome Interactions within the Sub-Ecosystems of an Extreme Environment. Oral presentation, UC Riverside Genetics, Genomics, and Bioinformatics Annual Symposium. October 2022, Riverside, California.

**Linton Freund**. Investigating the Aeolian Microbiome of the Salton Sea. Flash-talk, UC Riverside Genetics, Genomics, and Bioinformatics Annual Symposium. October 2020, virtual attendance.

### **SKILLS & TECHNIQUES**

Bioinformatics Experience

- Experience using a variety of bioinformatic tools to process and assess the quality of amplicon sequence data and shotgun metagenome sequence data including FastQC, Trimmomatic, Cutadapt, the BBMap suite, and DADA2.
- Experience assembling, binning, and annotating shotgun metagenome data as well as calculating read coverage using MEGAHIT, MetaSPades, MetaQUAST, BWA-mem, metaBAT2, checkM, Prodigal, KOFamScan, and featureCounts.
- Experience creating custom scripts using Bash shell and awk commands to process, filter, and merge large amplicon and shotgun metagenome datasets.
- Experience creating reproducible and accessible workflows that utilize a variety of bioinformatics tools using Rmarkdown and version control on GitHub, with associated releases on Zenodo.

### Statistical Analysis and Programming

- Experience using statistical techniques to analyze datasets including modeling-based methods (i.e., linear regressions, generalized linear models), ordination methods (i.e., principal components analysis, principal coordinates analysis, redundancy analysis, canonical correspondence analysis), and multivariate and univariate analysis of variance.
- Experience creating scripts and analytical workflows using R statistical software and Bash shell that guide users through how to analyze sequence data and geochemistry data for any research project.
- Experience managing and analyzing large datasets using Bash shell, R statistical software, and highperformance cloud computing clusters at universities.

#### Laboratory Skills

- Soil, seawater, and environmental dust sample collections and processing (i.e., vacuum filtration, sieving, etc.) based on the lab's standardized protocols.
- DNA extraction, DNA quantification, DNA purification, and PCR of environmental DNA for various research projects.
- Culturing microorganisms from isolated cultures (liquid and solid) or environmental samples on simple and complex media.

#### Other Skills

- Teaching basic coding in R statistical software and Bash shell, as well as guiding undergraduates and research scientists through coding and analytical tutorials.
- Experience in using Microsoft Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Slack, Discord, and GitHub.

#### **VOLUNTEER & COMMUNITY SERVICE**

# **UC Riverside Graduates for a Free Palestine** University of California, Riverside

Member, Co-Founder

Oct 2023 - May 2024 **Food Not Bombs** 

Riverside, CA Chapter Member

#### **Queer Graduate Student Association**

Sep 2021 - Sep 2024

University of California, Riverside

President (2022-2023), Vice President (2021-2022), Member (2020 – Present)

**UAW 4811** Sep 2021 - Present

United Auto Workers

Member (2023 – Present), Bargaining Team Representative Alternate (2022), Biosciences Departments Organizer (2021 - 2022)

## Genetics, Genomics, and Bioinformatics Student Association

Oct 2019 – June 2023

Oct 2023 - Sep 2024

University of California, Riverside

Vice President (2022-2023), Vice President (2020-2021), Student Representative Alternate (2019 – 2020)

## **Biology Graduate Student Association**

Aug 2018 - May 2019

California State University, Long Beach Board Member (2018-2019)

## **REFERENCES**

#### Dr. Emma Aronson

Professor, Microbiology & Plant Pathology Department University of California, Riverside

(951) 827 - 4201

emma.aronson@ucr.edu

Relationship: Dissertation project supervisor

#### **Dr. Will Porter**

Professor, Environmental Sciences Department University of California, Riverside (951) 827 - 1387

william.porter@ucr.edu

Relationship: Dissertation committee member, collaborator

## Dr. David Lo

Professor, Biomedical Sciences Department University of California, Riverside (951) 827 - 4553 david.lo@ucr.edu

Relationship: Collaborator

# Dr. Jason Stajich

Professor, Microbiology and Plant Pathology Department (951) 827 - 2363 jason.stajich@ucr.edu

Relationship: Dissertation committee member